#### **Curriculum Vitae**

### Hannah Wangui Ngugi

**Date of Birth**: 26<sup>th</sup> Sep 1977

**Age:** 36

Marital Status: Single No. Of Children: 1 Religion: Christian

**Address:** P.O. BOX 6972, 00100 Nairobi, Kenya

**Mobile Telephone:** +254 722 573 506

Email: nguqiwangui@gmail.com

#### **Profile**

A highly competent, driven and enthusiastic financial management/ accounting professional with over fourteen years of experience in both the NGO and private sector; with varied experience in preparing financial reports; implementing cash management strategies in the highest possible standards of excellence, transparency and compliance with all external regulations, accounting and financial management standards and internal policies and procedures. Hannah has a great track record in achieving sound development and monitoring of budgets for restricted funds and grants.

### **Core Competences**

- 1) Maintenance of accurate financial records and ability to prepare clear and accurate reports for informational, auditing and operational use.
- 2) Outstanding knowledge of several donors rules, regulation, reporting practices and procedures, Grant Management, Fund accounting and fiscal management.
- 3) Creative and resourceful thinking.
- 4) Ability to make quick and excellent decisions and organize thoughts in time constraints and full workload.
- 5) Outstanding communication, presentation and interpersonal skills.
- 6) Ability to achieve strong grasp of operations and implementation of various projects within the organization in a short time.
- 7) Sound Ability to handle multiple tasks, set priorities and meet deadlines.
- 8) Superb organizational and detail-oriented skills.
- 9) Ability to analyze and interpret financial data.
- 10) Sound knowledge, understanding and experience with Microsoft Dynamics Navision, QuickBooks accounting, fleetmax, Pastel Accounting, AccPAC, Account safe, FARS, and Microsoft Office.
- 11) Strong ability to train staff, evaluates, identify their best fit within finance and motivate them to grow within the Organization.

### **Key Achievements**

## **Achievements at African Academy of Sciences**

 In my current role I have overhauled the finance and administration processes and procedures, developed terms of reference for procurement of a financial management system which is currently under implementation, established a working procurement department, developed procurement, financial and travel policies which have been adopted, established a filling system for HR, established a performance review and development planning for staff, with support of executive director introduced additional benefits for staff and planned and executed recruitment of 10 additional staff in 2015 to setup of a program platform.

### **Previous Achievements at Samaritans Purse**

- 2) Have been involved in the process of rolling out an in-house accounting software through critiquing, highlighting areas of improvement, training staff and being the overall administrator.
- 3) Development of TOR for procuring Financial Management System up to contracting and implementation.
- 4) Part of the team that formulated and standardized the procurement system which is currently being used by all Samaritan's Purse Field offices, and follow up on Implementation for the Kenya Office.
- 5) Have managed over \$15m annual budgets for Kenya and South Sudan Programs with funding from USAID (OFDA/PEPFAR), CHF, CIDA, UNICEF (Kenya and Sudan), GOAL South Sudan and internal funding from SP Head Office and affiliate offices.
- 6) Coaching and training of staff on financial management, budgeting, funds Management, 3 of the staff trained are serving as Finance Manager with Samaritan's Purse in different African countries.
- 7) Leading the process of reviewing the Finance Manual, HR Manual, Travel Policy.
- 8) Building of a strong team by providing leadership, clear goals and timelines for achieving set objectives.
- 9) Putting up a strong cash management system, which has reduced the cash transaction by 70% for the last 4 years.
- 10) Formulated and overhauled the cash advance system which helped reduce the time staffs were holding cash before turning in reports the system is still being used and adopted by other field offices.
- 11) Establishing a working relationship with Program Managers and assisting them to do proper monthly cash projection based on their activity plans.
- 12) Established a stock management system at Wines of the World Tanzania branch, the system helped reduce on stock loss and ensuring proper pricing during invoicing.
- 13) Establishing stock control system aimed at reducing stock loss and pilferage.

## **Employment History**

African Academy of Sciences: Nov 2014 - To date Position Held: Finance and Admin Manager Reporting to: Chief Operating Officer

### **Key Responsibilities:**

- 1. Financial Management
- 2. Procurement Management
- 3. Payroll Management
- 4. Office Administration Management
- 5. Working closely with the COO, the role has significant input into the human resources, infrastructure and risk management
- 6. Developing, documenting and implementation of quality policies, systems, procedures and processes

### **Financial Management**

- Prepare and present, monthly and annual Academy's financial reports against budgets in an accurate and timely manner;
- Analyse variances from income and expenditures on a monthly basis
- Manage the preparation of financial statements for each programme/ donor as per the timing required by each funder
- Coordinate the preparation of and management of the annual audit process, in liaison with the COO.
- Oversee and lead annual budgeting and planning process in conjunction with the COO; administer and review all financial plans and budgets; monitor progress and changes and keep senior leadership team abreast of the organization's financial status.
- Manage the preparation of a rolling forward 6 months Cash flow budget reviewed on a weekly basis in separate currencies.
- Advise on placements and uplifting of investments as per the investment Policy.
- Implement and manage a robust contracts management and financial management/ reporting system; ensure that financial data and cash flow are steady and support operational requirements.
- Update and implement all necessary organizations policies and accounting practices;
   improve the finance department's overall policy and procedure manual.
- Effectively communicate and present the critical financial matters to the COO.

#### **Human Resources Role**

- Supporting the COO in HR Administration and Management
- Ensuring that the Staff Development and Performance Plan is implemented by all staff.
- Ensure that recruiting processes are consistent and streamlined.
- Following the implementation of individual staff development plans manage a comprehensive training program to train on needs as well as educating employees regarding staff tools, policies and procedures.
- Oversee the Payroll management and statutory payment are made within the legal requirements.
- Work closely and transparently with all external partners including third-party vendors and consultants.

### **Administration Role**

- Oversee administrative functions which includes Office functions such as:
  - o Cleaning Services and Managing the Kitchen.
  - Managing Maintenance and Repairs works.
  - Security Services.
  - Maintaining Office utility services efficiently.
- Oversee the procurement process and ensure that proper procedure and guidelines
- In conjunction with the COO ensure that third party vendors and consultants meet their expectations in service provision.
- In conjunction with the COO, ensure that the MIS function is optimum this includes:
  - The server and systems in use are working at an optimum for the institution.
  - Back up of official data generated by staff are regularly backed up.

# AGRA (Alliance for Green Revolution in Africa): Feb 2014 – October 2014 Position Held: Finance Officer.

Reporting to the Finance Manager, my key duties include:

- Reviewing vendor payment request, processing payment and reconciliation of Vendor accounts;
- Budget posting and review for grantee budgets the system;

- Review grantee reports to ensure compliance with requirements, and making recommendation to the grants unit for funds disbursement;
- Processing new grantee awards in the system;
- Reviewing IRS(International Recruited staff) benefit claims and processing for payments;
- Reviewing Travel Expense Claims and staff Reimbursements.
- Preparing donor Reports.

# Samaritan's Purse (SP) - International Relief: September 2007 – Jan 2014 Position Held: Finance Manager.

Reporting to the Country Director, my key responsibilities include but are not limited to:

- Providing oversight on compliance of accountancy procedures: filing of documents, allocation of expenses, vouchers registration, balance checking etc;
- Verify and compile monthly accounts from field offices; Send reports on a monthly basis to HQ, following organizational procedures and deadlines;
- Open/close bank accounts on the authority of HQ: Oversee the management of bank accounts, follow transfers, check balances; Supervise the management of safes and cash: available amount, balance checks, security instructions;
- Assess monthly cash-flow needs for projects and bases and communicate cash requests to the HQ on a monthly basis; Manage money transfers, bases cash-supply and amounts in circulation, whilst defining payment procedures (bank transfer, cheque, cash etc.);
- Set up and formalize procedures for the commitment of expenditure, conform to SP's procurement guidelines: define methods and timescales for payment according to Kenya practices and availability of funds; Ensure that procedures are adhered to in terms of contracts and payments; Ensure that proofs of purchase are valid (contracts, orders, bills, invoices, delivery receipts etc);
- Develop tables necessary for financial monitoring and for budget follow up within the Organization; Analyze gaps between planned budgets and actual expenses; Anticipate financial risks;
- Develop budgets for project proposals according to project needs and Donor constraints; Draft financial reports (mid-term and final) respecting contractual deadlines; Guarantee the respect of Donor procedures for each financial contract.
- Participate in training & induction of staff to the procurement system;
- Ensure overall compliance with the procurement policy; participate in selection of bids to ensure transparency in the process; scrutinizing supplier details etc;
- Oversee the team and undertake appraisals of directly supervised colleagues; Ensure training and capacity building for finance team in order to increase the level of technical ability and skills within the department;
- Develop relevant management procedures within the team; Improve information flows within the department and with other departments and projects.
- Closely work with the HR and Admin Manager on payroll administration, application of expat work permits, and procurement of office services and goods.

# Samaritan's Purse - International Relief: May 2004 - August 2007 Position Held: Accountant

Reporting to the Finance Manager, my key responsibilities included but were not limited to:

- Producing accurate and timely and financial and management accounts to facilitate planning for the Kenya and Southern Sudan Projects;
- Assisting Finance Manager in Preparation of various donor reports as per donor requirements and guidelines accurately and on a timely basis;
- Vetting and approval of supplier's payments;
- Providing guidance, training and daily supervision of the, Finance assistant, and field logisticians in their area of responsibility;

- Preparing Bank reconciliations;
- Assisting the Finance Manager with both internal and external annual audit.

# Wines of the World and Fine Foods and Wines: January 2003 – April 2004 Position Held: Management Accountant

My key responsibilities included but were not limited to:

- Posting of stock purchases, expenses, banking receipts and payments;
- Reconciling the daily cash, Bank statements, and petty cash;
- Participating in the monthly stock take;
- Preparation of monthly management financial reports;
- Ensuring compliance with statutory requirements;
- Maintaining the filing system and carrying out any administrative duties;
- Performing internal audit function in the Tanzania branch to establish cause for stock loss;
- Training of Wines of World Tanzania staff on Pastel Accounting Software.

# Mobil Oil Convenience stores: January 2002— December 2002 Position Held: Book keeper Supervisor

- Daily posting of purchases, stock, receipts, credit cards, debtors invoices etc;
- Rotational stock checks on specific categories and financial records management;
- Handling supplier's invoices and processing them for payments;
- Compiling of sales reports and profit and loss analysis reports whilst co-coordinating shop promotions;
- Computing and filling VAT returns;
- Ensuring the adherence to procedures and internal controls;
- Maintaining the petty cash account and preparing a petty cash disbursements statements;
- Reconciling the fuel sales with the bank receipts and updating such records in the system;
- Ordering of goods from suppliers and ensuring timely payments;
- Ensuring the shop is well stocked and clean as per set standards;
- Changing staff shift and balancing sales and cash available;
- Ensuring that customer are given proper service;
- Supervisory of all shop attendant staff

### **Training**

- MANGO: Training of Trainers (Taking fear out of Finance): November 2013
- INSIDE NGO: USAID rules and regulations workshop; May 2008
- CPM: Management of USAID/CDC Cooperative Agreement, Mastering USAID Rules and Regulations & Maximizing Recovery of Direct and Indirect Cost; July 2010

### **Education**

UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL UNIVERSITY, International Business Administration (Finance) - 2006

KENYA ACCOUNTING & SECRETARIATE NATIONAL EXARMINATION BOARD, Certified Public Accountant of Kenya (CPA-K) – 2001

KENYA ACCOUNTING & SECRETARIATE NATIONAL EXARMINATION BOARD, Kenya Accounting Technician Certificate (KATC) - 1997

MARY LEAKEY GIRLS HIGH SCHOOL, Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education- 1995

# Interests

I consider myself a dynamic and vibrant person and have varied interests. I enjoy travelling, hiking, networking as well as reading self-motivating books. I am passionate about giving back to my community and I have managed to do this through the Rotaract Club of Milimani where I served as Community and Professional Director and also through the interactions and relationships that come my way either through family, friends, work and my church.

#### References

### DR. Patrick Gitonga, Deputy Country Director

Samaritan's Purse – International Relief P.O. BOX 76143-00508 Tel +254-789-510-336 Nairobi, Kenya pqitonga@samaritan.org

#### **Terrie J. Blevins**

Samaritan's Purse – International Relief Régional Finance Manager P O Box 3000 - 801 Bamboo Road Boone, NC 28607 (828) 262-1980 Ext. 1498 tjblevins@samaritan.org

### Peter Shewan, Managing Director,

Alexanna Ltd
P.0 Box 63284-00619 Tel +254-727-335-800
Nairobi Kenya
peter@alexanna.co.ke

### George K. Rutto, Head of Internal Audit

Consolidated Bank
P.O. BOX 51133 – 00200 Tel +254-735-337-020
Nairobi, Kenya
grutto@consolidated-bank.com

## Millicent Ndirangu, Regional Brand Manager

Nestlé Equatorial African Region P O Box 50813-00200 Tel +254-20-498-4422 Nairobi, Kenya millicent.ndirangu@ke.nestle.com